[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
today i'm talking to jonathan sherriet
he's the co-author of tragic design the
host of the design review podcast and
he's currently a senior interaction
designer and accessibility program lead
at google
jonathan welcome to software engineering
radio hi jeremy thank you so much for
having me on
the title of your book is tragic design
and i think that
people can
take a lot of different meanings from
that so i wonder if you could start by
explaining what tragic design means to
you
for me it really started with this story
that we have in the beginning of the
book it's also online i originally wrote
it as a medium article
and that's really what opened my eyes to
hey design is this kind of invisible
world all around us
that we actually depend on very
critically in some cases and so this
story was
about a girl a nameless girl but we
named her jenny for the story
and
in short she came for treatment of
cancer at the hospital
was given the medication
and the nurses that were taking care of
her were so distracted with the software
they were using to chart make orders
things like that
that they missed the fact that she
needed hydration and that she wasn't
getting it and then because of that she
passed away
and
i still remember that feeling of just
kind of outrage
and we hear a lot of news stories a lot
of them are outraging
they they touch us
but some of those feelings stay and they
stick with you and for me that stuck
with me i just couldn't let it go
because i think a lot of your listeners
will relate to this like we get into
technology because we really care
about
the potential of technology what can it
do what are all the awesome things that
could do if we come out a problem and we
think of all the ways it could be solved
with technology and here it was doing
the exact opposite it was causing
problems it was causing harm and the
design of that or you know the way that
was built or whatever it was failing
jenny it was failing the nurses too
right like a lot of times we blame that
end user
and that causes so to me that story was
so tragic
something that
deeply saddened me and was regrettable
and cut short someone's life and that's
the definition of tragic and there's a
lot of other examples with varying
degrees of tragic but as we look at the
impact technology has and then the
impact we have in creating those
technologies that have such large
impacts we have a responsibility to
really look into that and make sure
we're doing as best of job as we can and
avoid those as much as possible because
the biggest thing i learned in
researching all these stories was hey
these aren't bad people
these aren't people who are
clueless and making these terrible
mistakes they're me they're you they're
people just like you and i that can make
the same mistakes
i i think it's
pretty clear to our audience where
there was a loss of life someone died
and that's clearly tragic right so i
think a lot of things in
the
healthcare field if there's a real
negative outcome whether it's death or
severe harm
we can clearly see that as tragic
and i know in your book you talk about a
lot of other
types of
i guess negative things that software
can cause
so i wonder if you could explain a
little bit about now past the death and
the severe injury
what's tragic to you
yeah still in that line of like of
injury and death the side that most of
us will actually impact our work
day-to-day is also physical harm like
creating the software in a car i think
that's a fairly common one but also
ergonomics right like when we bring it
back to something less impactful but
still like multiplied over the impact of
a product rather
it can be quite big right like if we're
designing software in a way that's very
repetitive or everyone's got that scroll
thumb scroll issue right
our phones aren't designed well so
there's a lot of ways that it can still
physically impact you ergonomically and
that can cause you a lot of problem
arthritis and pain there's other ways
that are still really impactful so the
other one is by saddening or angering us
that emotional harm is very real and
oftentimes
sometimes gets overlooked a little bit
because it's you know physical harm is
what is so real to us but sometimes
emotional harm isn't
but you know we talk about in the book
the example of facebook
putting together this great feature
which takes your most liked photo
and
celebrates your whole year by saying hey
look there's a hearing you're in review
there's the top photo from the year they
add some great you know well done
illustrations behind it of of balloons
and confetti
and people dancing
but
some people had a bad year some people's
most you know liked engaged photo is
because something bad happened
and they totally missed this
and because of that people had a really
bad time with this where you know they
lost their child that year they lost
their loved one that year their house
burnt down something really bad happened
to them
and here was facebook putting that photo
of their dead child up with balloons and
confetti and people dancing around it
that was really hard for people they
didn't want to be reminded of that and
especially in that way and these
emotional harms also come into the in
the play of lying around anger
you know we talk about well one there's
a lot of software out there that tries
to bring up news stories that anger us
and which equals engagement
but also ones that use dark patterns to
trick us into purchasing and buying and
forgetting about that free trial so they
charge us for a yearly subscription and
won't refund us like if you've ever
tried to cancel a subscription you start
to see some real they're real colors
so emotional harm and anger is a big one
we also talk about injustice in the book
where there are products that are
supposed to be providing justice
in very real ways like voting
or
getting people the help that they need
from the government
or for people to see their loved ones in
jail
or you know you're getting a ticket
unfairly because you couldn't read the
sign was you're trying to read the sign
and you and you couldn't understand it
we look at a lot of different ways that
design and the software that we create
can have
very real impact on people's lives and
in a negative way if we're not careful
the impression i get when you talk about
tragic design it's really about
anything that
could harm a person whether physically
emotionally you know make them angry
make them sad
and
i think the
most liked photo example is a great one
because like you said i think people may
be building something that harms and
they may have no idea that they're doing
it
exactly like i love that story because
not to just jump on the back wagon of
you know of saying bad things about
facebook or something no i love that
story because
i can see myself designing the exact
same thing like being a part of that
product building it looking at the
specifications the pm that put together
and the decks that we had you know like
i could totally see that happening and
just never i think never having the
thought because we're so focused on like
delighting our users and we have these
metrics and these things in mind so
that's why like in the book we really
talk about a few different processes
that need to be part of that product
development cycle
to stop pause and think about like well
what are the negative aspects here like
what are the things that could go wrong
what are the other life experiences that
are negative that could be a part of
this and you don't need to be a genius
to think of every single thing out there
you know like in this example i think
just talking about oh well some people
might have had if they would have taken
probably like one hour out of their
entire project maybe even 10 minutes
they might have come up with oh there
could be bad things right but so if you
don't have that moment to pause that
moment to just say okay we have
time to
brainstorm together about like how this
could go wrong or how you know the
negative of life could be impacted by
this feature that's all that it takes it
doesn't necessarily mean that you need
to do some
giant study around the potential impact
of this product and all the ways but
really just having a part of your
process that takes a moment to think
about that will just create a better
product and better
product outcomes you know if you think
about all of life's experiences and
facebook can say
hey condolences and like and show that
thoughtfulness
out of higher engagement that would have
higher
satisfaction right so they could have
created a better outcome by considering
these things and obviously avoid the
negative impact to users and the
negative impact to their product
continuing on with that thought you're
a senior interaction designer and you're
an accessibility program
lead
so i wonder on the projects that you
work on and maybe you can give a
specific example but how are you
ensuring that you're not running up
against these problems where you build
something that you think is going to be
really great for your users but in
reality ends up being harmful in
specific cases
yeah one of the best ways is i mean it
should be part of multiple parts of your
cycle if you want
something if you want a specific outcome
out of your product development a life
cycle it needs to be from the very
beginning
and then a few more times so that it's
not i think programmers will
all latch on to this where they have the
worst end of the stick
right because in qa as well because any
bad decision or assumption that's
happened early on with the business team
or the pm it gets like multiplied when
they talk to the designer and then gets
multiplied again they hand it off and
it's always the engineer who has to put
the final foot down be like this doesn't
make sense or i think users are going to
react this way or you know this is the
implication of that assumption it's the
same thing in our team we have it in the
very early stage when someone's putting
together the idea for the the feature or
project we want to work on it's right
there there's a few there's like a
section about accessibility
and a few other sections talking about
like looking out for this negative
effect so right away we can have a
discussion about it when we're talking
about like what we should do about this
and the different
implications of implementing it
that's the perfect place for it maybe
when you're brainstorming
about like what should we should do
maybe it's not okay there because you're
trying to be creative right you're
trying to think but at the very next
step when you're saying okay like what
would it mean to build this
that's exactly where i should start
showing up and the discussion from the
team
and it depends also the risk involved
right like which is attached to how much
time and effort and resources you should
put towards avoiding that risk it's risk
management so if you work like my
colleagues or some of my friends who
work in the automotive industry
and you're creating a software and
you're worried that it might be
distracting
there might be a lot more time enough or
the healthcare industry those might need
to take a lot more resources but if
you're maybe building sas software for
engineers to spin up their
resources there might be a different
amount of resources and never zero
because you still have are dealing with
people and you'll impact them
and maybe that service goes down and
that was a health care service that went
down so you really have to think about
what the risk is and then you can map
that back to how much time and effort
you need to be spending on getting that
right and accessibility is one of those
things too where a lot of people think
that it takes a lot of effort a lot of
resources to be accessible it really
isn't it's just like tech debt you know
like if you have ignored your tech debt
for
five years and then they're saying hey
let's i'll fix all the tech debt yeah
nobody's gonna be on board for that as
much
versus like if addressing that and
finding the right level of tech debt
that you're okay with and when you
address it and how and just better
practices that's the same thing with
accessibility is like if you're just
building it correctly as you go it's
very low effort and it just creates a
better product better decisions and it
is totally worth the increased amount of
people who can use it and the improved
quality for all users so
yeah it's just kind of like a win-win
situation
one of the things you mentioned was that
this should all start
at the very beginning or at least right
after you decide on what kind of product
you're going to build
and that's going to make it much easier
than if you come in later and try to
make fixes then
i wonder when you're all getting
together and you're trying to come up
with these scenarios try to figure out
negative impacts what kind of
accessibility
needs you need to have
who are the people who are involved in
that conversation like you know you have
a team of
50 people who needs to be in the room
from the very beginning to start working
this out
i think it would be the same people who
are there for the project planning and
my team
we have our eng counterparts there at
least the team lead
if there's a lot of them but if they
would go to the project kickoff
they should be there we have everybody
there pm design engineers
our project manager anyone who wants to
contribute should really be there
because the more minds you have with
this the better you'll tease out much
much more of all the potential problems
because you have a more
diverse
set of brains and life experiences to
draw from and so you'll you'll get
closer to that 80 mark
that you can just quickly take off a lot
of those big items off the table right
off the bat
is there any kind of
formal
process you follow or is it more just
people are thinking up ideas putting
them out there and just having a
conversation
yeah again it depends which industry
you're in what the risk is so i
previously worked at a healthcare
industry
and for us to make sure that we get that
right and how it's going to impact the
patients especially that you know as
cancer care and they were using our
product to get early warnings of adverse
effects our system of figuring that you
know if that was going to be an issue
was more formalized
in some cases like healthcare
especially if if it's a device or in
certain software circumstances it's
determined by the fda
to be a certain category you literally
have a governmental
version of this
so the only reason that's there is
because it can prevent a lot of harm
right so that one is enforced but
there's reasons outside of the fda to
have that exact formalized part of your
process the size of it should scale
depending on what the risk is so on my
team the risk is actually somewhat low
it's really just part of the planning
process we do have a moment when we're
brainstorming like what we should do and
how the future will actually work
where we talk about like what those
risks are and calling out the
accessibility issues and then we address
those and then as we are ready to
get ready to ship we have another
formalized part of the process there
where we check if the accessibility has
been taken care of and if everything
makes sense as far as the impact to
users so
we have those places but in healthcare
it was much stronger where we had to
make sure that we've tested it it's
robust it's going to work when we think
it's going to work we do user testing it
has to pass that user testing things
like that before we're able to ship it
to the end user
so in
healthcare you said that the fda
actually provides is it a checklist of
things to follow where you must have
done this kind of user testing and you
must have verified these things that's
actually given to you by the government
that's right yeah it's like a checklist
and the testing requirement and there's
also levels there so i've only done the
lowest level i know there's two more
levels above that and again that's like
because the risk is higher and higher
and there's more stricter requirements
there where maybe somebody in the fda
needs to review it at some point and
again like mapping it back to the risk
that your company has is really
important understanding that is going to
help you avoid and build a better
product avoid the bad impact and build a
better product and i think that's one of
the things i would like to focus on as
well and i'd like to highlight for your
listeners is that
it's not just about avoiding
tragic design because one thing i've
discovered since writing the book and
sharing it with a lot of people
is that the exact opposite thing is
usually in a vast majority of the cases
ends up being a strategically great
thing to pursue
for the product and the company you know
if you think about that example with
with facebook okay you've run into a
problem that you want to avoid but if
you actually do a 180 there and you find
ways to engage with people when they're
grieving you find people to develop
features that help people who are
grieving
you've created a value to your users
that you can help build the company off
of right
because they were already building a
bunch of joy features right
you know and also like user privacy like
we see apple doing that really well
where they say okay we are gonna do our
ml on device we are gonna let users
decide on every
permission and things like that and that
is a strategy we also see that with like
something like t-mobile when they
initially started out they were like one
of the
nobody telecoms in the world and they
said okay what are all the unethical bad
things that our competitors are doing
they're charging extra fees
they have these weird data caps that are
really confusing and don't make any
sense they're contracts you get locked
into for many years they just did the
exact opposite of that
and that became their business strategy
and it worked for them now they're the
top company so i think there's a lot of
things like that where you just look at
the exact opposite
and one you get to avoid the bad tragic
design but you also boom you see an
opportunity that can become a business
strategy
so when you refer to exact opposite i
guess you're you're looking for the
potentially
negative outcomes that could happen
there was the facebook example of of
seeing a photo or being reminded of a
really sad event and figuring out can i
build a
product around
still having that same picture but
recontextualizing it like showing you
that picture in a way that's not gonna
make you sad or upset but is is actually
a positive yeah i mean i i don't know
maybe what the solution was but like one
example that comes to mind
is some companies now before mother's
day
will send you an email and say hey this
is coming up do you want us to send you
emails about mother's day because for
some people that can be very painful
that's very thoughtful right and that's
a great way to show that you that you
care
think about that facebook example like
if there's a formalized way to engage
with with giving like i would use
facebook for that i don't use facebook
very often or almost at all but you know
if somebody passed away
i would engage right with my my facebook
account and i would say okay look
there's like there's this whole
formalized you know feature around
and facebook understands grieving and
facebook understands this event and like
smooths that process creates comfort for
the community that's value and
engagement that it's worthwhile versus
artificial engagement that's for the
sake of engagement and that would create
a better feeling towards facebook i
would maybe like then you spend more
time on facebook so it's in their mutual
interest to do it the right way and so
it's great to focus on these things to
avoid harm but also to start to see new
opportunities for innovation and we see
this a lot already
in accessibility
where there's so many innovations that
have come from
just fixing accessibility issues like
closed captions we all use it on our tvs
in busy crowded spaces on videos that
have no translation for us in different
places so
seo is the same thing like you get a lot
of seo benefit from
describing your images and making
everything semantic and things like that
and that also helps screen readers and
different innovations have come because
somebody wanted to solve an
accessibility need and then the one i
love i think is the most common one is
readability contrast and text size
sure there's some people who won't be
able to read it at all but i i hurts my
eyes to read bad contrast and bad text
size
and so it just benefits everyone creates
a better design and one of the things
that comes up so often when i'm on the
accessibility program lead and so i see
a lot of our bugs
is so many issues that are caught
because of our audits and our test cases
around accessibility that just are bad
design and are a bad experience for
everyone and so we're able to fix that
and it's just another driver of
innovation and there's a ton of
accessibility examples and i think
there's also a ton of these other
ethical examples or avoiding harm where
it's an opportunity area where it's like
oh let's avoid that but then if you turn
around you can see that there's a big
opportunity to create a business
strategy out of it can you think of any
specific examples where you've seen that
where somebody you know doesn't treat it
as something to avoid but but actually
sees that as an opportunity i think that
the apple example is a really good one
from the beginning they saw like okay in
the market there's a lot of abuse of
information and people don't like that
so they created a business strategy
around that and that's become a big
differentiator for them they have like
ml under the device they have a lot of
these permission settings you know
facebook was very much focused right on
using customer data and a lot of it
without really asking their permission
and so once apple said okay now all apps
need to show what you're tracking and
and ask for permission to do that a lot
of people said no and that caused about
10 billion dollars of loss for facebook
and for apple it's they advertise on
that now that we're ethical that we
source things ethically and we care
about user privacy and that's a strong
position right i think there's a lot of
other examples out there like i
mentioned accessibility and others but
like they're kind of overflowing so it's
hard to pick one
yeah and i think what's interesting
about that too is with the example of
focusing on user privacy or trying to be
more sensitive around
death or things like that is i think
that other
people in the industry will will notice
that and then in their own products then
they may start to incorporate those
things as well
yeah yeah exactly with the example with
t-mobile
once that worked really really well and
they just ate up the entire market
all the other companies followed suit
right like now having those data caps
are very rare having those surprise fees
are a lot rarer
there's no more like deep contracts that
lock you in and et cetera et cetera like
a lot of those have become industry
standard now
and it doesn't improve the environment
for everyone because that becomes a
competitive advantage that everybody
needs to meet
so yeah i think that's really really
important so when you're going through
your product's life cycle you might not
have the ability to make these big
strategic decisions like you know we
want to not have data caps or whatever
but if you're on that facebook level and
you run into that issue you can say what
could we do to address this what we
could do to to help this and make make
that a robust feature we talk about a
lot of these dating apps one of the
problems was a lot of abuse
where women were being harassed or after
the day didn't go well that you know
things were happening and so a lot of
these dating apps have differentiated
themselves and attracted a lot of that
market because they deal with that
really well and they have you know it's
built into the strategy so it's often
times like a really good place to start
too because one it's not something we
generally think about very well which
means your competitors haven't thought
about it very well which means it's a
great place to build products ideas off
of
yeah that's a good point because i think
so many
applications now are
like social media applications their
messaging applications their their video
chat that sort of thing
when those applications were first built
they didn't really think so much about
what if someone is you know sending
hateful messages or sending pictures
that people really don't want to see
people are doing abusive things it was
like they just assumed that oh people
will be
people will be good to each other and
it'll be fine but in the last 10 years
pretty much all the the major social
media companies have tried to figure out
like okay
what do i do if someone is being abusive
and and what's the process for that and
basically they all have to do something
now
yeah and it's a hard thing to like if
that unethical or that bad design
decision
is deep within your business strategy
and your company strategy it's hard to
undo that some companies still have to
do that very suddenly and deal with it
right like
i know uber
had a big big part of that and like and
some other companies but we're like
almost suddenly everything will come to
a head and they'll need to deal with it
twitter now trying to trying to get be
acquired by elon musk
some of those things are coming to light
but
what i find really interesting is
that these areas are really ripe for
innovation so if you're interested in
a startup idea or you're working in a
startup or you know you're about to
start one
there's a lot maybe a lot of people out
there who are thinking about side
projects right now this is a great way
to differentiate and win that market
against other well-established
competitors
is to say okay well what are they what
are they doing right now that is
unethical and it's core to their
business strategy and doing that
differently is really what will help you
to win that market and we see that
happening all the time you know
especially the ones that are like these
established
leaders in the market they can't pivot
like you can so being able to say we're
going to do this ethically we're going
to do this with this tragic design in
mind and doing the opposite that's going
to help you to find your attraction in
the market earlier we were talking about
how
in the medical field there is specific
regulation or at least requirements to
try and avoid this kind of tragic design
i noticed you also worked for intuit
before
so for
financial services i was wondering if
there was anything similar where the
government is stepping in and saying
like you need to make sure that these
things happen to avoid these harmful
things that can come up yeah i don't
know i mean i didn't work on turbo tech
so i worked on quickbooks which is like
a accounting software for small
businesses and i was surprised like we
didn't have a lot of those robust things
we just relied on user feedback to tell
us like things were not going well and i
think we should have like i think that
was a missed opportunity
to
show
your users that you understand them and
you care and to find those opportunity
areas so
we didn't have enough of that and there
was things that we shipped
that didn't work correctly right off the
box which you know it happens but had a
negative impact to users so it's like
okay what do we do about that how do we
fix that the more you formalize that
make it part of your process
the more you get out of it and actually
this is a good pausing point that i
think will affect a lot of engineers
listening to this
so if you remember in the book we talk
about the ford pinto story and the
reason i want to talk about this story
and why i added it to the book
is that one i think is the thing that
engineers deal with the most
and designers do too which is that okay
we see the problem
but we don't think it's worth fixing
okay that's what we're gonna dig into
here so so hold on for a second while i
explain some some history about this car
so the ford pinto if you're not familiar
is notorious
because it was designed and built and
shipped and they knowingly had this
problem where if it was rear-ended at
even like a pretty low speed
it would burst into flames because the
gas tank would rupture
and then often times the doors would get
jammed and so it became a death trap of
fire
and caused many deaths a lot of injuries
and in an interview with the ceo at the
time almost destroyed ford very
seriously would have brought the whole
company down
and during the design of it and design
meaning in the engineering sense and the
engineering design of it they found this
problem and the engineers came up with
their best solution was this rubber
block and the cost was
i forget how many dollars let's say it
was like nine dollars i say six dollars
but this is again back then and also the
margin on these cars was very very very
thin and very important to have the
lowest price in the market to win those
markets the customers were very price
sensitive so they they being like the
legal team
looked at like some recent cases where
they had the value of life and started
to come up with like here's how many
people would sue us and here's how much
it would cost to settle all those and
then here's how much it would cost to
add this to all the cars
and it was cheaper for them to just go
with the lawsuits they found
and i think i think why this is so
important is because of the two things
that happened afterward one they were
wrong
it was a lot more
people it affected and the
lawsuits were for a lot more money
and two
after all this you know was going crazy
and and it was about to destroy the
company they went back to the drawing
board and what did the engineers find
they found a cheaper
solution
they were able to rework that rubber
block and get it under the margin and be
able to hit the mark that they wanted to
there's a lot of focus on the first part
because it's so unethical the value of
life and doing that calculation and
being like we're willing to have people
die but
in some industries it's really hard to
get away with that but it's also very
easy to get into that it's very easy to
get lulled into this sense of like oh
we're just gonna crunch the numbers and
see how many users it affects and we're
okay with that
versus when you have principles and you
have kind of a hard line and you and you
care a lot more than you should and
and you really push yourselves to create
a more ethical more a safer avoiding
tragic design
there's a solution out there you
actually get to innovation you actually
get to solving the problem versus when
you just rely on oh you know the cost
benefit analysis we did is that it's
going to take an engineer you know a
month to fix this and blah blah blah
if you have those values if you have
those principles and you're like you
know what we're not okay shipping this
then you'll find that they're like okay
there's there's a cheaper way to fix
this there's another way we could
address this
and it happens so often and i know a lot
of engineers deal with that a lot of
saying like oh you know this is not
worth our time to fix this is not worth
our time to fix and that's why you need
those principles is because oftentimes
you don't see it but it's right there
right outside of the edge of your vision
yeah i mean with the pinto example i'm
just picturing
you know obviously there wasn't jira
back then but you can imagine that
somebody having an issue that hey when
somebody hits the back of the car it's
going to catch on fire and and going
like well how do i prioritize that right
like is this a medium ticket is this a
high ticket and it just seems insane
right that you could make the decision
like oh no this isn't that big an issue
you know we can move it down to low
priority and and ship it yeah and that's
really what principles do for you right
is they help you make the tough
decisions you don't need a principle for
an easy one
and that's why i really encourage people
in the book to come together as a team
and come up with what are your guiding
principles and that way it's not a
discussion point every single time it's
like hey we've agreed that this is
something that we're going to care about
this is something that we are going to
stop and fix like one of the things i
really like about my team at google is
product excellence is very important to
us
and there are certain things that we're
okay with letting slip and fixing at the
next iteration and
we make sure we actually do that so it's
not like we always address everything
but because it's one of our principles
we
care more we have more we take on more
of those tickets and we take on more of
those things and make sure that they're
fixed before we ship
and it shows like to the end user that
this company cares and they have quality
you need a principle to kind of guide
you through those difficult things that
aren't obvious on a decision to decision
basis but you know strategically get you
in somewhere
important like design debt or technical
debt where it's like
this should we optimize you know this
chunk of code like nah
but in
grouping together with a hundred of
those decisions yeah it's gonna it's
gonna slow down every single project
from here on out
so
that's why you need those principles
so in the book there are a few examples
of software in
healthcare
and when you think about
principles you would think that
generally everybody on the team would be
on board that we want to give
whatever patient that's involved we want
to give them good care we want them to
be healthy we don't want them to be
harmed
and
given that i'm wondering because you you
interviewed multiple people in the book
you have a few different case studies
why do you think that
medical
software in particular seems to be so
it seems to have such poor ux or has so
many issues
yeah that's a complicated topic i would
summarize it with a few like maybe three
different reasons one which i think is a
maybe a driving factor of some of the
other ones is
that the way that medical
industry works is
the person who purchases the software is
not the end user so it's not like you
have doctors and nurses voting on on
which software to use
and so oftentimes it's more of like a
sales deal and then just gets pushed out
and they also have to commit to these
things like the software is very
expensive and
initially in the early days was very
much like needs to be installed
maintained there needs to be training so
there was a lot to money to be made
in that software the investment from the
hospital was a lot so they can't just be
like okay we actually don't like this
one we're gonna switch to the next one
so because like once it's sold it's
really easy to just keep that customer
there's very little incentive to like
really improve it unless you're selling
them a new feature so there's a lot of
feature add-ons because they can charge
more for those but improving the
experience and all that kind of stuff
there is less of that i think also
there's just generally a lot less
understanding of design
and that field because they're sort of
like traditions of things they end up
putting a lot of the pressure and the
responsibility on the end individuals
so you know you've heard recently of
that nurse who had made a medication
error
and she's going to jail for that and
oftentimes we blame that end person so
the nurse gets all the blame or the
doctor gets all the blame well what
about the software you know who like
made that confusing or you know what
about the medication that looks exactly
like this other medication or what about
the pump tool that you have to type
everything in very specifically and the
nurses are
very busy they're doing a lot of work
they're having 12 hour shifts they're
dealing with lots of different patients
a lot of changing things
for them to have to worry about having
to type something a specific way and yet
when those problems happen what do they
do they don't go and like redesign the
devices and
they
more training more training more
training more training and people only
can absorb so much training
and so i think that's part of the
problem is that like there's no desire
to change
they blame the wrong person
and
lastly i think that it is starting to
change i think we're starting to see
like the ability because of the fact
that the government is pushing
healthcare records to be more
interoperable meaning like
i can take my health records anywhere
that a lot of the power comes in where
the the data is and so
i'm hoping that you know as the
government and people and and
initiatives push these big companies
like epic to
be more open
that things will improve one is because
they'll have to to keep up with their
competitors and that more competitors
will be out there to improve things i
think that there's the know-how out
there but like because there's no
incentive to change and there's no like
turnover in systems and there's the
blaming of the end user we're not going
to see a change anytime soon
that's a good point in terms of like it
seems like even though you have all
these people who may have good ideas may
want to do a startup
if you've got all these hospitals that
already locked into this very expensive
system
then
where's the room to kind of get in there
and have that change
yeah
another thing that you talk about in the
book is about
how when you're in a crisis situation
the way that a user interacts with
something is very different and i wonder
if you have any specific examples for
software when that can happen
yeah designing for crisis is a very
important part of every software because
it might be hard for you to imagine
being in that situation but it
definitely will still happen so
one example that comes to mind is
let's say you're working on cloud
software like aws or google cloud right
there's definitely use cases and user
journeys in your product where somebody
would be very panicked right and if
you've ever been on an on call
with with something and it goes south
and it's a big deal you don't think
right right like when we're in crisis
our brains go into a totally different
mode of like that fight-or-flight mode
and we don't think the way we do it's
really hard to read and comprehend very
hard and we might not make this the
right decisions and things like that so
thinking about that like maybe you're
let's say going back to that the cloud
software like let's say you're working
on that are you relying on the user
reading a bunch of text about this
button or is it very clear from the way
you've crafted that exact button copy
and how big it is and it's where it is
relation to a bunch of other content
like what exactly it does it's gonna
shut down the instance or it's gonna do
it at a delay or whatever like all those
little decisions like are really
impactful and when you when you run them
through the furnace of a user journey
that's relying on on a really urgent
situation
you'll obviously help that you'll start
to see problems in your ui that you
hadn't noticed before or different
problems in the way you're implementing
things that you didn't notice before
because you're seeing it from a
different way and that's one of the
great things about the systems in the
book that we talk about around like
thinking about how things go go wrong or
you know thinking about designing for
crisis
is it makes you think of some new use
cases which makes you think of some new
ways to improve your product that
improvement you make to make it so
obvious that someone could do it in a
crisis would help everyone even when
they're not in a crisis
that's why it's important to focus on
those things
and for someone who
is working on these products
it's kind of hard to trigger
that feeling of crisis if there isn't
actually a crisis happening so i wonder
if you can talk a little bit about how
you you try to design for that when it's
not really happening to you you're just
trying to imagine what it would feel
like yeah you're never really going to
be able to do that so some of it has to
be simulated one of the ways that we are
able to sort of simulate what we call
cognitive load which is one of the
things that happened during a crisis but
would also happen when someone's very
distracted they might be using your
product while they're multitasking they
have a bunch of kids a toddler
constantly pulling on their arm and
they're trying to get something done in
your app so
one of the ways that has been shown to
help test that is like the foot tapping
method so when you're doing user
research you have the user doing
something else like tapping or like
making so like they have a second task
that they're doing on the side that's
manageable like tapping their feet and
their hands or something and then they
also have to do your task and you can
like build up what those extra things
are that they have to do while they're
also working on
finishing the task you've given them
and that's one way to sort of simulate
cognitive load some of the other things
is really just listening to users
stories and finding okay like this user
was in crisis okay great let's let's
let's talk to them and interview them
about that it was fairly recently within
like the past six months or something
like that
but sometimes you don't like you just
have to run through it and do your best
and
those black swan events or those
even if you're able to simulate it
yourself like put yourself into that
exact position and be in panic
which you know you're not able to but if
you were that still would only be your
experience and you wouldn't know all the
different ways that people could
experience this so there's gonna be some
point in time where you're gonna need to
extrapolate a little bit and extrapolate
from what you know to be true but also
from user testing and things like that
and then wait for real data
you have a chapter in the book on
design that anchors and there were there
were a lot of examples in there on on
things that are just annoying or you
know make you upset while you're using
software
i wonder for like our audience if you
could share just like a few of your
favorites or your ones that really stand
out
my favorite one is clippy because you
know i remember growing up writing
documents and clippy popping up
and i was reading an article about it
and obviously just like everybody else i
hated it as a little character it was
fun but like when you're actually trying
to get some work done it was very
annoying
and then i remember a while later
reading this article
about how
much work
the teams put into clippy like i mean if
you think about it now it had a lot of
like so the ai that we're playing with
just now around like natural language
processing understanding like what type
of thing you're writing and coming up
with contextualized responses like it
was pretty advanced for the very
advanced for the time adding animation
triggers to that and all all that and
they had done a lot of user research i
was like what you did research and like
you had that reaction
and i love that example oh and also by
the way i love how they took clippy out
and highlighted that as like one of the
features of the next version
of the office software but i love that
example again because i see myself in
that and you know you have here you have
a team
doing something technologically amazing
doing user research and putting out a
very great
product but
totally missing the point
and a lot of products do that a lot of
teams do that and why is that
it's because they're not thinking about
they're putting the business needs or
the team's needs first and they're
putting the user's needs second
and whenever we do that whenever we put
ourselves first we become a jerk right
like if you're in a relationship and
you're always putting yourself first
that relationship is not going to last
long or it's not going to go very well
and yet we do that with our relationship
with users where we're constantly just
like okay well what is the business the
business wants you know users to not
cancel here so let's make it very
difficult for people to cancel
and that's a great way to lose customers
that's a great way to create
this dissonance with your with your
users
and if you're
focused on like this is what we need to
accomplish with the users and then you
work backwards from there you'll lower
your chances of missing it of getting it
wrong of angering your users and always
think about sometimes just be very real
with yourselves and your team i think
that's really hard for a lot of teams
because we don't want to look bad what i
found is those are the people who
actually
get promoted
you know if you look at the managers and
directors those are the people who can
be brutally honest right who can say
like i don't think this is ready i don't
think this is good i've done that in the
front of like our ceo and things like
that and i've always had really good
responses from them to say we really
appreciate that you you can call that on
you can just call it like it is like hey
this is what we see this user maybe we
shouldn't do this at all you know at
google that's one of the criteria that
we have in our software engineers and
our designers of being able to spot
things that are things that we should
stop doing and so i think that's really
important for the development of a
senior engineer to be able to know that
that's something like hey this project i
would want it to work but in its current
form is not good and being able to call
that out is very important
do you have any specific examples where
there was something that was like
very obvious to you but to the rest of
the team or to a lot of other people it
wasn't
yeah so here's an example i i
finally got i was uh early on in my
career and i finally got to lead in a
whole project so we were redesigning our
business micro site
i got us assigned to engineers and
another designer and i got to lead the
whole thing i was like this is my chance
right so and we had a very short
timeline as well and i put together all
these designs and
one of the things that we aligned on at
the time was like as really cool as i
put together this really cool design for
the contact form where you have like
essentially a kind of like ad lib it
looks like a letter
by the way give me a little bit of
leeway here because this was like 10
years ago but uh it was like a letter
and and you would say like you're
addressing it to our company and so it
had all the things we wanted to get out
of you around like your company size
your team like
and so our sales team would then reach
out to this customer i designed it and i
had shown it to the team and everybody
loved it like my manager signed off on
it like all the engineers signed off on
it even though we had a short timeline
they're like yo we don't care that's so
cool we're gonna build it
but as i put it through that test
of does this make sense for the what the
user wants
the answers just kept being no to me so
i had to go and back in and pitch
everybody and argue with them
around not doing the cool idea that i
wanted to do
and eventually they came around and that
form performed once we launched it
performed really well and i think about
like what if users had to go through
this really wonky thing like this is the
whole point of the website is to get
this contact form it should be as easy
and as straightforward as possible so
i'm really glad we did that and i can
think of many many more
of those situations where
we have to be brutally honest with
ourselves like this
isn't where it needs to be or this isn't
what we should be doing and we can avoid
a lot of harm that way too where it's
like i don't think this is what we
should be building right now
so in the case of this form was it more
you had a bunch of drop downs or
selections where you would say like okay
these are the types of informations i
want to get from the person filling out
the form as a company
but you weren't looking so much at as
the person filling out the form this is
going to be really annoying was that
kind of exactly okay exactly like so
their experience would have been they
come at the end of this page or on like
contact us and it's like a letter to our
company
and like we're essentially putting words
in their mouth because they're they're
filling out the letter and then yeah
it's like you know you have to like read
and then understand like what that part
of the page was asking you and versus a
form where you're you know it's very
easy well known bam you're you're on
this page so you're interested it's like
get it get them in there
so we were able to decide against that
we also had to say no to a few other
things we said yes to some things that
were great like responsive design
making sure that our website worked at
every single use case which is not like
a hard requirement at the time but was
really important to us and ended up
helping us a lot because we had a lot of
business people who were on their phone
on the go who wanted to check in and
fill out the form and do a bunch of
other stuff and learn about us so
that sales microsite did really well
because i think we made the right
decisions in all those kind of areas and
like those those general those
principles helped us say no to the right
things even though it was a really cool
thing it probably would have looked
really great in my portfolio for a while
but just wasn't the right thing to do
for the goal that we had
so did it end up being more like just a
text box you know a contact us
yeah you know with usability if
someone's familiar with
something and it's
tired everybody does it but that means
everybody knows how to use it so
usability constantly has that problem of
innovation being less usable
and so sometimes it's worth the
trade-off because you want to attract
people because of the innovation and
they'll get over that hump with you
because the innovation is interesting so
sometimes it's worth it i'd say most
times it's not and so you have to find
like when is it time to innovate and
when is it time to to do what's tried
and true and on a business microsite
i think it's time to do tried and true
so in your research for the book and all
the jobs you've worked previously are
there certain
mistakes or just ux things that you've
noticed that you think that our audience
should know about
i think dark patterns are one of the
most common
tragic design mistakes that we see
because again you're putting the company
first and the user second
and if you go to dark patterns.org
you can see a great list there's a few
other sites that have a nice list of
them and actually vox media did
a nice video about dark patterns as well
so it's gaining a lot of traction
but you know things like if you try to
cancel your cert like comcast service or
your amazon service it's very dark i
think i wrote this in the book but i
researched what's the fastest way to
remove your comcast account i prepared
everything
i did it through chat because that was
the fastest way not to mention finding
chat by the way was very very hard for
me even though i was like okay i have to
find i'm gonna do it through chat i'm
gonna do all this it took me a while to
find like chat and like i couldn't find
it so once i finally found it from that
point to deleting from having them
finally delete my account
was about an hour
and i knew what to do going in just to
say all the things to just have them not
bother me so that's on purpose they've
purposely because it's easier to just
say like fine i'll take the discount
thing you're throwing in my face at the
last second and it's almost become a
joke now that you have to
cancel your comcast every year so you
can keep the cost down
you know in amazon too like trying to
find that delete my account is like so
buried and they do that on purpose and a
lot of companies will do things like
make it very easy to sign up for a free
trial and hide the fact that they're
going to charge you for a year hide the
fact that they're automatically gonna
bill you not remind you when it's about
to expire so that they can surprise get
you and to forget about this billing
subscription or like you know if you've
ever got adobe software
they are really bad with that they trick
you into like getting this like monthly
suspicion but actually you've committed
to a year and if you want to cancel
early we'll charge you like 80 of the
year and it's really hard to contact
anybody about it so it happens quite
often if the more you read into those
different things different patterns
you'll start to see them everywhere
and users are really catching on to a
lot of those things and respond to
to those in a very negative way we
recently looked at a case study where
this company had a free trial and they
had like the standard free trial kind of
design
and then their test was
really just focusing on like hey we're
not gonna scam you if i had to summarize
that the entire direction of the second
one it was like
cancel any time here's exactly how much
you'll be charged and on it'll be on
this date and five days before that will
remind you to cancel and all this stuff
that ended up performing about 30
better than the other one and the reason
is that people are now burned by that
trick so much so that every time they
see a free trial they're like forget it
i don't want to deal with all this
trickery like
i don't even care about to try the
product versus like hey we're not going
to trick you we really want you to
actually try the product and you know
we'll make sure that if you're not
wanting to move forward with this that
you have plenty of time and plenty of
chances people respond to that now so
like that's what we talked about earlier
in in the show of doing the exact
opposite this is another example of that
yeah because i think a lot of people are
familiar with like you said trying to
cancel comcast or trying to cancel their
new york times subscription and they you
know everybody is just
like they get so mad at the process but
i think they also maybe assume that it's
a positive for the company but what
you're saying is that maybe that's
actually not in the company's best
interest yeah oftentimes what we find
with these like dark patterns or these
unethical like decisions is that they're
successful because
when you look at the most impactful like
immediate
metric you can look at it looks like it
worked you know let's say for that those
free trials it's like okay we
implemented like all this trickery and
our subscriptions went up but if you
look at like the end
result
which is like farther on in the process
it's always a lot harder to track that
impact but we all know like when we look
at each other like when we
we talk to each other about these
different examples like we know it to be
true that we all hate that and we all
hate those companies and we don't want
to engage with them and we don't some
sometimes we don't use the products at
all
so it's one of those things where
it actually has like that very
real impact but harder to track
and so oftentimes that's how these
patterns become very pervasive is page
views went up this is high engagement
but it was page views because people
were refreshing the page trying to
figure out where the heck to go right so
oftentimes they're less effective but
they're easier to track
so i think that's a good place to wrap
things up but if people want to check
out the book or learn more about what
you're working on your podcast where
should they head
just check out tragicdesign.com
and our podcast you can find on any of
your podcasting software just search
design review podcast
jonathan thank you so much for joining
me on software engineering radio all
right thanks jeremy thanks everyone hope
you had a good time i did
this has been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening